[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software engineering today we
are talking to James Phillips from Hashi
Corp at Hashi Corp James works on
console and surf he also developed fault
tolerant avionics for spacex and called
out flight software is go during the
first SpaceX missions to the ISS he has
also worked on web applications and
embedded systems today we will be
talking to him about service discovery
welcome to software engineering radio
change thanks for having me on the
podcast it's good to be here I do have a
bit of an odd mix in my background of
sort of embedded things and web
applications but I think it was good
training for what I do at Hoshi core
with real time mixed with distributed
systems great so why don't we dive in
then so can you tell us at a very high
level what is service discovery so at
the highest level it's basically a
system that lets you say where is
service foo and that answer is usually
something in the form of an IP address
and a port number and a service can be
kind of a logical entity within your
architecture so you might have you know
a database or you might have a pool of
application servers things like that so
usually there's a set of processes that
back a given service and usually for
most highly available things or scalable
things there's there's more than one
process that makes up a service and
service discovery lets you find those
things on kind of a spectrum of maybe if
you could have a fully statically
configured service discovery system or a
very very dynamic service discovery
system so the the techniques you use to
do service discovery vary a lot
depending mostly on sort of how fresh
the information is and how changes get
put into your service discovery catalog
so when you say a very static
configuration that makes
we think of just using configuration
files where I might update them
occasionally and I could use a
configuration management tool like
puppet or chef what's wrong with that
approach that approach can work okay
when you have a small handful of things
you manage but as soon as you get even
sort of a large ish medium largest to
very large infrastructure it becomes
very very hard to keep that catalog
up-to-date by hand the times involved to
do a convergence run can you know run in
two minutes
and that's often not fast enough to
propagate a change and also just the
having a human in the loop to sort of
check in changes to that catalog manage
a list of IPs and then Avis's to push
that out becomes a burden in a system
that you know you want to run as
automatically as possible so it becomes
kind of a maintenance burden and a
response time problem for an
infrastructure once it gets beyond any
you know once it's beyond sort of a
trivial scale that gets really really
hard to manage right I can imagine even
at a small scale you mention response
time if you need response time it's
still gonna take a while yeah if your
database you know if you do a master
failover and you want to point all your
clients is somewhere else you know you
want that change to go out quickly you
don't want that to take you know ten two
minutes to propagate to your system so
the configuration management tools have
definitely have a role even even if
you're using a service discovery system
for bootstrapping new nodes or kind of
getting the service discovery system
kicked off but in terms of managing sort
of the ongoing state of your
infrastructure yeah it becomes very very
difficult to do with a sort of a static
set up oK we've been talking about scale
that kind of hints to kind of larger
networks what what network scope is
appropriate for service discovery sort
of land datacenter and cross datacenters
my short answer to that is yes it's it
can have a place basically at all those
those different sort of levels so you
know within an application you you
wouldn't necessarily have it you know
within a process isn't you're not gonna
find like components or plug-ins with a
service discovery mechanism but once you
have a process trying to find out where
enough
processes it's appropriate there and
then when you get into highly available
or globally distributed infrastructures
it definitely makes sense for you know
some service in data center a to reach
out and find an instance of another
service in data center B so it makes
sense
usually there's sort of a preferential
scope you want to use things that are
close and nearby and then as you know
sometimes it's part of normal operations
to find things remotely or you know in a
much larger tier across the internet and
it definitely makes sense when you're
talking about you know geo redundancy
and failover and things like that so you
want ideally your service discovery
system would let you cross those
boundaries without having to have like a
totally separate instance that's totally
disconnected and your application has to
know about how to go reach out to all
these different things okay you know a
local network would service discovery be
comparable to the zero configuration
networking something like the Apple
Bonjour is that a form of service
discovery it definitely is in terms of
sort of the most basic you know where
what's the IP or port of an instance of
this type of service we'll see later
there's other facets of service
discovery like managing other types of
configuration or orchestration where
something like that probably isn't ideal
and it's also a system that often
requires dependence on things like
multicast and features like that so it's
I that's like sort of a low-level piece
that might be part of a bigger service
discovery solution after you if you look
at sort of a full spectrum of what you
need in a complete solution but it's
it'd be a very limited form of service
discovery so you mentioned processes
finding one another can you tell us some
more about some scenarios where service
discovery would be appropriate when you
talk about processes finding each other
I think of something like a
service-oriented architecture possibly
micro service is definitely a service
discovery I think even for a monolithic
application your basic configuration
like where's the database how do I
connect to it that even makes sense in
that type of architecture but as you
move to service-oriented or micro
services
you're gonna have sort of a much more
distributed set of pieces that need to
find each other you'll have much more
sort of dynamic environment in terms of
different pieces of your architecture
coming going over time in general you'll
have more than one instance to choose
from so you'll want to choose a healthy
one to talk to so the things get a lot
more dynamic as you have a an
architecture that's distributed across
more sort of functional pieces the
service discovery really shines there
and then in the extreme if you're
running under a resource scheduler like
kubernetes or meso sort of nomads you'll
have your your pieces are placed onto
machines and your cluster basically by a
an automated infrastructure so at that
point there's basically no chance to
have you know humans editing config
files and pushing out changes you need
something that in real time can manage
where all your resources are and which
ones are healthy and and where to find
them
okay are there applications or scenarios
where I wouldn't want to use service
discovery I don't think so I think the
basic sort of hygiene of separating the
configuration out of your application is
a good thing to start with early on you
know it's you don't want to be hard
coding IP addresses you know in your
source code whatever in the extreme so
you you're gonna want some separation
there from the beginning and I think
it's also easy to sort of progressively
use different features of service
discovery mechanisms as your application
gets more sophisticated so they with a
service discovery system that supports a
DNS interface you can use service
discovery by just you know having your
application look up a host name so you
can have like essentially a zero-touch
integration even very early on and then
in overtime you might need to use
orchestration features to elect a leader
among many potential leaders and your
pool services and things like that so
it's possible to sort of start simple
within an integration that's very very
lightweight or essentially even zero
impact your application code and then
expand from there but to start that way
versus hard-coding or maintaining these
things is a good way to go and also in a
world where you might be building a Mis
and you know machine images and things
like that
it's a nice like separating out the
service discovery piece into a separate
layer is handy for not having to you
know make a new ami when some
configuration changes so having that
layer in there can even have practical
implications for your deployment
pipeline and and just how you manage
your your your images for deployment
okay so yeah that's you said something
there that I was that made me think
about immutable infrastructure and
certainly if you're talking about baked
in am eyes and actually extracting out
this variable configuration information
that would make sense right yeah and
yeah having that layer there and then
being able to dynamically push changes
out after something's deployed without
having to actually you know and
basically get into that image and change
its configuration is is a super big plus
and that same ami can connect to any
database or connect to any instance of
your API server or whatnot because it's
getting all that configuration on the
fly from the service discovery system
okay so yeah move at least the
configuration related variability out of
your infrastructure all right that makes
sense let's move into some more kind of
technical details what data are
typically stored in service discovery
repositories you mentioned host names or
IPs and port numbers is that kind of the
extent of it or is there more that's
sort of the most fundamental data but
when you get into managing services
there and their configuration you
generally need a little bit more
information so you'll typically have
things like you know database username
potentially credentials tokens like
other configuration type information
that goes along with the basic IP import
information that that's already stored
in the surface coverage system it's also
a good place to put things like feature
flags
there's kind of a general bucket of key
value for
that nearly every service discovery
system supports which is useful for
capturing basically the whole set of
configuration data that you might need
for interacting with other services okay
yeah I was gonna ask about something as
something like database credentials or
something so those could be in service
discovery and then I hadn't even thought
of feature flags so what are the you
mentioned kind of a key value storage
thing what are typical components of
service discovery tool so the sort of if
you want to take a complete solution for
service discovery it really comes down
to four different pieces so there's the
core service discovery so you know where
is this thing
what's its IP and port how do I kind of
connect to it any complete solution
generally needs a health monitoring
piece it's not really interesting to get
you know an instance that's no longer
functioning when you're looking for
something to connect to so having a
health monitoring component creates a
really sort of fresh and live set of
data that's gonna be very easy to manage
with you in your infrastructure you need
some configuration storage so that's
generally in the form of a kv store key
value store and that can also be used
for coordination so we can talk about
some applications around that and then
an orchestration piece so it's often
useful to be able to to say among many
possible instances help have tools to
elect a leader or make sure that a
certain operation is done in a way that
doesn't have any race conditions or even
some systems even lets you do things
like send events out or you know run
commands dude like certain more dynamic
things if you want to have a an event go
out across your fleet and cause some
action to happen things like that
okay would load-balancing be a function
of service discovery or is that gonna be
something separate it can be and many
it's sort of an architectural choice
with different service discovery systems
so some sort of make load-balancing
first-class part of of the architecture
so Yool Yool
all your traffic get some kind of load
balancer and the novel man is talking to
different healthy instances it's often
the case though where you can actually
avoid load balancing with the service
discovery system and avoid that whole
tier and potential point of failure so
if you can if you can talk directly to a
healthy instance by virtue of how your
service discovery system works it's
actually kind of nice to avoid load
balancing if you can like there's
different trade-offs and there's
different choices one common thing is
sort of within your data center you
might not use load balancers at all and
you use your service discovery system to
manage handing out healthy here's a
healthy instance of this service talk to
this guy and if it fails you can get a
new one but then you'll use your service
discovery system to configure an
external load balancer that your
customers are using say like that your
website you know IP addresses are
pointed to so that you can have
combinations of things and some systems
run load balancers internally that you
know route traffic over overlay networks
and things like that so there's there's
quite a range of different solutions
there okay
so how do servers that they want to
offer a service how do they know where
they're gonna register to and on the
flip side of that the clients that are
looking for a service work how do they
know I mean you know do we need another
layer of service discovery yeah I think
it'd be Turtles yeah it sort of Turtles
all the way down for services Gary you
generally need some kind of seed or some
way to introduce a new entity into the
service discovery system some systems do
that with you know some well-known DNS
some serve records for some you know
route service to talk to Hoshi groups
console has a Atlas join feature so we
actually have a free sort of hosted
joining service that'll help you find
other nodes to talk to initially and
there's also different architectures in
terms of how you access the service
discovery system console for example
runs an agent on every node so your
applications only ever talk to their
local agent and the console kind of
manages how to talk to servers and how
to route your requests around other
systems you might have to locate sort of
a central server and make requests
against that
there's different strategies but there
usually is some sort of bootstrapping
process or service that you need to kick
things off okay yeah that makes sense
you said the said seed and yeah at some
point in time all the way down to the
following all the turtles down we get an
egg or a scene there yeah there's a
there's maybe a hard-coded IP address or
something similar somewhere but there's
yeah things like a let's join make that
pretty easy like you can have a well
known thing to reach out to and it will
manage finding you a server to join with
okay yeah I want to touch on Atlas
towards the end here but in the meantime
given that service discovery the way
we've been talking about it it's gonna
be used possibly by pretty much the
whole app you know even trying to find
the database and things like that it's
gonna need to be fairly reliable what
are some features or characteristics of
service discovery tools that provide the
reliability yeah that's that's
definitely a prime concern for a system
like this which could potentially be a
it'd be sort of like a nuclear single
point of failure if it wasn't if it
wasn't done properly so a key component
of nearly any district or any service
discovery system is to be distributed
and replicated so you need to be able to
basically build out redundancy to
whatever level of failure tolerance you
want and that may mean having redundancy
within your say kind of a local area
network kind of scope so you might have
multiple servers and then you may also
want redundancy by having sort of
different Federation's of servers that
can talk to each other it might be in
different geographic locations and
things like that so having a distributed
system with replication that can handle
you know if server going completely
offline or two servers or whatever level
you want to proficient to is very
important and then there's also the
concerns of dealing with you know what
happens when the system is down
altogether so in the event of a
partition or something like that there's
different strategies for say say like if
you had
a system that has a consensus algorithm
and requires a certain number of servers
for a quorum and if you get below that
number of servers so maybe you can't
make rights to your system anymore you
can't make any changes you still want
the reads to work well so there's tools
that are exposed to the clients to say
hey I'm I'm willing to take some stale
information I just want to you know
what's your best information that you
had as a you know this long ago or what
not so you want it to operate even in
sort of degraded modes and fail
gracefully and and kind of at a very
practical level there's a lot of sort of
techniques that good service discovery
solutions have in terms of you know
managing how they deal with retries and
how they avoid thundering herd's when
things come back online you know how do
they randomize traffic to spread load of
Mon different components how do you
scale certain events based on the size
of the clusters and things like that so
there's quite a bit of layers that go
into making a robust service discovery
system that's gonna keep working no
matter what ok and and when you say
distributed system we mean sort of in
the classic sense of three or five or
seven servers and you mentioned a
consensus algorithm possibly and so then
that kind of gets would get us into the
cap theorem for example right in terms
of making some decisions or trade-offs
there yes and there's definitely the
different tools have different
strategies and different trade-offs and
there's there are AP type systems and
they had like you know that we can give
some examples of specifics but there are
systems that make sort of more of an AP
sort of bent that will have better
availability but potentially much harder
to reason about failure modes where you
might end up with you know two different
sides of your cluster working in two
different ways and then there are
systems that go more the CPU route so
those are often easier to reason about I
think for operators and provide they
have a consensus algorithm to let you
kind of know the state of your cluster
and have a known behavior in the event
that things go wrong that's fairly easy
to reason about so there's different you
know kinda pending on your application
that there's there's different
considerations but I would say most
systems tend towards a CP type
architecture so for frying consistency
and and partition tolerance over
availability yeah but with the caveat
that you have sort of a read level of
veil ability even in the loss of a you
know a loss of quorum say so you know
you need to think about that case and
not have it just knock out but you know
the minority that can't make progress in
terms of making rights can still read
the current state as it was at the time
the partition happened for example okay
yeah that makes sense
we've mentioned a couple of times about
databases suppose you know rather than
running my own database server I'm
hosting in Amazon AWS and I'm using
their service for RDS to provide my my
sequel or Postgres server would I still
be using service discovery to discover
the database even though in theory
Amazon's gonna keep it pretty stable for
me I think so because we tools like
console have support for what we call
external services so those are those are
static registrations but they are served
in the same manner in terms of consoles
api's as any other service okay so yeah
consistency so you're not special casing
Amazon that's right so you can manage it
sort of in the same place you could
retrieve it in the same way and then as
you if you were gonna you know manage
some portion of your database
infrastructure yourself it'll sort of
nicely ramp into being supported by
console without changing your clients so
it's it's like getting that sort of
basic hygiene of having all your
configuration in one place you can you
can definitely do that with external
services right and it also gives you the
flexibility than if everyone's using the
same pattern to make different decisions
in the future that's right it and the
overhead is pretty low I mean it's you
know it's it's it's one level of
indirection which software engineers are
always ok with just one more level of
indirection
one more level and we can solve any
problem that's right so how important is
security in a service discovery tool do
we need to use cryptography either to
encrypt the communications or
authenticating clients and servers
security is pretty huge I mean in this
system basically will direct your you
know your internal services to connect
to things and make requests to them it
could be key to finding you know where
the database is you could potentially
have credentials in there so yeah we any
actual production deployment of a
service discovery system needs to think
about security you know generally people
use TLS to secure all the traffic it's
usually important to verify the identity
of your servers so you can also use you
know certificate verification like you
don't want sort of random nodes on your
network joining on as servers and
potentially interfering with the quorum
or you know a rogue amount that can push
bad data in there things like that and
then on top of sort of the basic
transport level stuff most tools also
involve some layer of access control
type tools available within the service
discovery system itself so you can scope
who's going to be able to you know
create new entries who can delete things
who can update key values which you know
you can segment your paths to where
different parts of your organization can
kind of self manage different parts of
your service discovery system okay and
then I would also think it probably
depends or could depend on kind of the
scope of the network that you're being
that you're using if if we're just
talking about a local area network or a
rack on premises that might be different
than if you were talking about a number
of nodes trying to find each other on
Amazon it could be yeah I mean it
definitely different practices might
make sense in different ways that sort
of different levels of organization
things like that but it's like it's
generally good to start with TLS and you
know some of the basics in there and
then you might only
are creating Apple policies once your
organization gets complex or you get a
couple different teams using the same
service entry system so some of that can
evolve but it's good to have just sort
of a basic level of transport security
under that underneath as a sort of a I
just call that sort of like a baseline
set up okay
you've mentioned console as a service
discovery tool and obviously I mean you
work on it and we'll discuss that in a
moment but what are some of the other
tools that are out there in this space
that you know I don't expect you to be
an expert on any or all of them and we
certainly don't have time to to dive
into them but just for other thing other
tools that listeners might be interested
in sure and I'm definitely yeah I'm not
an expert in every service discovery
system out there now I do work on
console full time so that's right I know
the most but there's a class of tools
that I would roughly kind of lump into
sort of key value stores so like
zookeeper @cd Doozer and console
actually has a key value store as well
and these sort of generally provide kind
of a highly available key value store
that can be accessed by clients and they
often include mechanisms like
coordination so locking type features so
you can have it you can actually
coordinator round a key and make sure
that the updates are atomic they
generally include some kind of help
checking notion to where a client will
maintain a connection and if the
connection closes something can happen
in the key value store so you can kind
of know that you know this is this guy
there's some notion of some client being
alive and a way to have the server's
help manage that and then these
generally couple some type of consensus
algorithm to provide a distributed
replicated key store so the main thing
that differentiates these different
solutions and where console is a little
bit unique is these often I think of as
kind of like lower-level toolkits so you
can build service discovery systems on
top of these but they don't necessarily
have
maybe as deep a mapping of all the
service discovery concepts in a form
that's easy to use so they're kind of
like a building block piece but not
necessarily you know a full solution so
like they might have basic health
checking in the form of monitoring a TCP
connection or having like a check and
kind of thing with a central server but
you wouldn't be able to do more general
health checking things like you know
running a Nagios script or something
like that
and they also they often don't handle
some of the sort of more global scales
we talked about like going you know
spanning different geographic regions
and things like that
that's generally left to be sort of
something that a client manages so a
full sort of service discovery solution
I think would encompass more than most
of the sort of basic key value stores
have but they're as sort of a building
block they're capable of doing pretty
powerful service discovery type things
yeah we talked about in episode 229 of
the podcast we talked about zookeeper
and yeah it was more on the level of the
key value store and coordination
algorithms and whatnot rather than high
level things like service discovery yeah
and there's other solutions there's
things like Sky DNS so it is sort of a
DNS centric system that's backed by a
consistent distributed system under the
hood to manage the failure tolerance sky
DNS and console both have a DNS
interface which makes it really easy to
integrate with your existing
applications with essentially no
modification so you don't have to do a
deep sort of client integration you just
look up a host and you know get ports
from serve records and things like that
so there's different features in these
different products but Skynet s is one
and console has a DNS interface and then
there's more there's others that are
sort of more unique kind of hybrid
solutions like smart stack sort of
composes several different pieces and it
uses zookeeper under the hood and it
actually uses zookeeper first sort of
it's consistent database and then it
uses h8 proxy
as its load-balancing layer and kind of
manages all those pieces together for
you so it's kind of a unique
architecture that has I'd say it's it's
a little more complicated but it has
like a very specific opinion about you
know you're going to use a load balancer
I'm going to manage the load balancer
for you and then it composes several
pieces around that and there's things
like Eureka from Netflix which has it
actually has sort of an eight more of an
AP sort of style to it and it has some
of the pieces of the basic like find me
an IP import it has less of the
coordination sort of general KB store
type features so it's a different mix
and they all these have different health
checking strategies there's a different
mix of sort of basic interface type
things like some have thicker clients
some have really lightweight clients
some have zero clients like DNS
interfaces so they among all these there
are many different types of
architectures most solutions though I
would say cover something on the order
of like you know one fifth to three
fifths of what I would consider kind of
an ideal scope for a full service
discovery solution though so many of
these tools you know if I'll do one part
really well but they require you to
build to get you know better health
checking or you you know you might have
really good knowledge of where services
are with IP imports things like that but
you don't have a key KB store so you'd
have to use something else there so most
of these would require you to compose
several things together to get a
complete solution okay so speaking of
complete solutions
perhaps we can then dive into your
wheelhouse so to speak and talk about
console so console is an open source
service discovery tool from Hoshi Corp
where you work at a high level what
features does it provide I mean you were
just discussing kind of trade offs or
how different different applications
have different sets of things that
they're bringing what does console bring
I think consoles unique
it I think it grew out of experience but
we had an earlier project which we still
use in as sort of the one of the basic
layers that consoles built on called
surf surf was an AP system that is used
to maintain kind of a basic list of
members and a cluster with some
additional metadata on them and to do
some health checking we'll talk a little
bit about how that fits in but in in the
experience with building surf and
thinking about you know what do
operators have to reason about what
should a service discovery system really
you know integrate together to do well a
console grew out of that and it really
comes down to four different pieces so
the basic service discovery piece that
we've talked about console focuses on
that but ties it to things like health
monitoring which is our second key
component at a deep level so it's it's
it's nice to have a good catalog but if
the catalog is out of date then you it's
not that useful
so by coupling the service discovery
engine with a really rich health
monitoring engine you have a much more
powerful service discovery system and
that's a set of tools you just use out
of the box so discovery health
monitoring configuration we mentioned
before like many of the systems
including KB store that's a key part of
console as well and we can talk about
this and utility even our configuration
store is tied in with our health
monitoring store which means it's tied
in with service discovery and then the
final pieces of orchestration so the
ability to coordinate with your service
discovery system the ability to send
events and you know kind of manage your
cluster in real time that's another key
component of console so tying all those
four pieces together is really what
makes console kind of stand out from the
rest it's it's got all those things sort
of thoughtfully integrated in a way
that's really easy to use and that will
do most of what people want right out of
the box okay what's kind of the basic
architecture you mentioned agents and
communicating with servers sure see the
the basic architecture console is that
you've run the console agent on every
node in your cluster so that's a it's
basically a single go binary and it's
easy to deploy and
that runs everywhere and then you'll
have some subset of your nodes that are
servers so you'll usually have like
three or five depending on your failure
tolerance three can handle one server
failure five can handle two so they'll
they run the same agent but it's in a
different mode it's in server mode so
each node is running an agent service
registration and health checks and all
those basic functions about what's going
on on a given node actually happened
with the agent on the node and then that
agent sinks the information back to the
servers and the server's run the raft
consensus algorithm to apply changes in
a in a consistent way to a state store
so it's a it's a little unusual and it's
something most people don't appreciate
it
first plants but the the agents are
actually the source of truth for all
your service configuration information
the servers manage central copy of that
which is the catalog and then they also
manage things that are sort of
information that belong to the whole
cluster like the KB store and your ACLs
and things like that so if you were to
say swap out your servers eventually
once the servers come back online the
agent will sink their service
configuration back up with the catalog
and you'll be off and running so it's
kind of an interesting division of labor
so the eight all of the agents have the
full key value store they don't so then
the agents have their configuration for
their nodes services and when you
request or make it when you make a
change that key key value store requests
a key those actually are requests that
are forwarded up to the servers okay so
they are managing truth for their local
node yes
okay and they're sinking that truth back
up with the servers and then the servers
maintain basically a central copy of
that truth as well as the key value
store so that's managed essentially by
the servers okay then what protocols
does console support for either the
service that's starting up that wants to
say I'm available
or the client that says I need to find
this service I believe you mentioned DNS
is one option that is one option so yeah
that so once you have the agent running
and you can configure different you know
you can disable these or enable these as
appropriate
the two main interfaces for talking to
it are the DNS interface and an HTTP API
and generally you'll you'll run the
agent on your local node and you'll have
your applications always just talk to
you know localhost port
8500 so your your applications allow is
just talk to console using their local
nodes agent interfaces and then behind
the scenes that agent is keeping track
of where the console servers are if a
server comes and goes it'll it'll put it
on the list so you know it'll it'll
manage that list of servers that are
possible when if a client uses the HTTP
API to say read a KB entry the local
agent will forward a request up to the
server and route the information back
and serve it to the client so the
clients always just talked to localhost
essentially and they can do it over HTTP
or DNS okay but if a servers publishing
you know saying I'm hearing available
that wouldn't be over DNS right that
would not also the and underlying the
console system we mentioned Cerf is sort
of under the hood there so as sort of a
background process each consul agent
does a periodic ping of another random
agent as well as an exchange of gossip
information so we there's a underlying
technology that's based on a academic
paper it's called swim but there's a
gossip protocol that's kind of a
low-level part of console so for example
when you join a new node you need
basically the only the address of one
other node and you'll talk to that one
learn about the other nodes in the
cluster and then start participating in
gossip and the random probing to check
for the aliveness of the other nodes so
that's a mechanism that your agent on a
given
we'll use to learn to it'll discover
that another server came online for
example through that process and that's
kind of a that's like a low-level part
of consoles architecture that's it's
extremely powerful because the the casa
player provides a built-in distributed
failure detector so consoles constantly
checking the health of all the nodes in
the cluster and maintaining membership
information about nodes that are coming
and going and the nice thing about swim
is that's done in a way that basically
has kind of a low volume constant level
of traffic that scales nicely across the
cluster so it's not you know some and
squared kind of thing it's a it's a
constant level where you know each at
each interval each node will pick one
other random node to probe and then
there's a gossip propagation mechanism
to get the information around nodes
coming and going around the cluster so
there's sort of an AP underpinning to
console that provides this information
of you know where the server which
servers are available this node is no
longer functioning that's kind of a low
level level of traffic that console
maintains automatically so it's
maintaining CP but or you said AP but
then console service itself is that ap
or is that more CPI I think you said
previously the events of say a node
coming or a node being declared dead
those propagate through the gossip layer
in sort of an AP fashion and then as
those events are recognized by the
server's they get fed into the catalog
in a consistent fashion so that when you
when you do service discovery you say
give me a healthy instance of this
service that's actually a request that's
going up to the servers and being done
based on the consistent view of the
cluster but there's a low-level sort of
ap view of the cluster that's being
constantly maintained and updated by all
the nodes in particular the distributed
failure detector so that nodes are
checking each other and then reporting
that information back up and then the
server's feed that into the to the
catalog using the consensus on rhythm
your view of the cluster is always
through kind of a lens of this
consistent catalog but the underlying
mechanism that helps realize that view
and provide the events of this node just
joined this one went away is is
happening by this gossip protocol under
the hood okay so that explains sort of
the the confusion is that there are at
least two distinct layers and they are
aligning themselves differently on the
cap triangle so to speak yeah it's a
little it's this is a really good place
for a diagram but formally it's exactly
it's a it's kind of a you can think of
you can almost think of yeah the surf
layer is kind of a yeah it's sort of a
layer that informs the consistent layer
but the consistent layer is what you use
for actually doing the service discovery
so it's kind of like a transport
mechanism but I don't want to create
more confusion there but it's a way to
you know move events around or say like
or announce that hey this server just
joined or this server is no longer
healthy I don't think we should be using
the services that were on it anymore
things like that okay if I've got an
application and it wants to find
services and whatnot and we talked about
doing that through DNS or HTTP but if
i'm using i'm i've got experience with
Ruby on Rails where we've got a whole
bunch of yml files do i need to rewrite
my application in terms of how it's
configuring itself instead of using yml
files or you know to do dns or HTTP or
is there another option there is and
it's very common to do this so in any
application that is driven by
configuration files we have some tools
and there are other community tools - in
particular there's something called
console template and there's another one
called in console and those are both
Hashmi Corp tools and what those do is
they'll do you'll run a process on a
given node it'll make a kind of a
blocking long pole request up to the the
console servers to watch for things to
change and
whenever a change is made to the
configuration they'll render a new
config file from a template in the case
of console template or that in the case
of end console they'll restart an
application and set environment
variables with configuration variables a
typical console and then you know send a
hub or restart a process so you can
basically get a closed-loop washer
that's looking for configuration to
changing console renders out a
configuration file and then restarts a
service or sends it up or you know
whatever sort of action you want to get
your service to reload its configuration
and that's a very very common glue into
existing applications is to just render
its config files directly from console
using one of these tools and have it get
restarted when things change and
similarly with the initial start we need
to run the template to generate the
config file then it's safe for me to
start my application and it'll just read
the config file exactly or you can yeah
you can you can use the console template
process just yeah generate that initial
config and then you know restart the
service which or let it start the first
time there's other console she has the
concept of watches too so you can
register a script with console and say
when anything changes with this service
or when a note is added or when somebody
touches this key run this script and
pass the information in is it basically
JSON on standard and so there there's
the capability to have sort of a
reactive script that's another way to
get at this information in an
application that otherwise doesn't know
much about console and there's a pretty
cool Mitchell wrote a thing called
console structure which is a go library
that lets you you basically get a
magical map that's driven by stuff and
console sort of piped directly into the
brain of your go application so like
there's there's different levels of
integration but it's super common to use
DNS and something like console template
to talk to an application that doesn't
have any knowledge of console at all
okay yeah that I can see how that would
be really helpful for the record when
you speak of Mitchell you're speaking of
Mitchell Hashimoto and we talked to
earlier on the show about
vagrant if people want to go and check
that out I wanted to ask another one of
these Turtles questions in terms of you
know so we've got a cluster of servers
three or five servers how do they start
out and find each other is that another
example of just kind of some seed
knowledge that's necessary they actually
use the same underlying join cluster
joint mechanism that's based on serve
but the the member information for a
server says it's a server and when when
you have an existing server that sees a
new one join it adds it to glue quorum
to the raft quorum and start us off
basically that there's kind of like a
parallel process to start up the
consensus algorithm but it's based on
the same event of hey this node just
joined and it's a server so you you
generally have to you know you generally
want to run multiple servers and consul
lets you for like a completely new
cluster there's a configuration called
bootstrap expect and let you say hey
there's going to be three so as soon as
you see three you know startup rafting
and start going once you have a cluster
that's already running it's also easy to
add more servers so if you wanted to go
from like a three server to a five
server configuration you can just do
that on the fly and there's a process
for reducing it as well so but in terms
of your experiences at console user the
way you join it to the cluster is very
similar you're just joining an agent
that's running in server mode okay
something you mentioned earlier Hoshi
Corp has a service called Atlas and I
believe it has both a free and a paid
for tier and I think of it sort of as a
unification of a number of Hachiko tools
can you tell us a little bit more about
Alice yeah so Alice is basically high
scores paid set of workflow tools that
builds on on top of our open-source
pieces so we've got a suite of products
console enterprises one of them the
other two or terraform enterprise and
vault enterprise and so there's a
there's a web-based
opponent to those that lets you manage
users like in the case of terraform you
can you can see a change it's going to
be made to the infrastructure have it
reviewed by somebody they can apply it
you know there's like kind of the the
workflow layer is provided by atlas in
consuls case there's a there's a free
piece of it called Atlas Auto join and
what this lets you do is solve that
initial turtle problem you let Atlas be
the turtle 0 at the base there so when
you bring a new node up and your cluster
you can say here's my cluster name
here's my atlas token I want to join and
it'll give you some addresses to join
your node to the cluster so it avoids
you having to manage like a fixed list
of servers or fixed IP lists for that
initial bootstrap and then the the paid
portion of console Enterprise gets you
features like a richer key value editing
interface so much you have
organizational permissions for different
parts of your key store and an interface
through Atlas to edit to view and edit
those and an alerts feature so you can
take consuls health checking information
and have those events feed into systems
like slack pager Duty HipChat
so you get a hosted solution that lets
you bridge onto those escalation
services and notification services
directly from console ok so the not to
sound dismissive but sort of a typical
open source strategy of most of the
tooling is open source and you can run
it yourself but when you get into
enterprise situations where they want
things like you mentioned access control
lists and other complexities that's
where the paid for service comes in
that's right so yeah it's it's sort of
like the management the workflow the
auditing like those types of pieces or
what Atlas provides and it's working in
concert with console which has an open
source you know an open source component
you could you could build a page or duty
escalator thing yourself or you could
use Atlas you know that that type of
strategy right ok makes perfect sense so
as we wrap up is
anything else you'd like to tell our
audience about console or service
discovery I mean I'm sure it's a huge
topic there's one there's kind of a pair
of features that I think is worth
mentioning that's pretty unique to
console so we mentioned that as part of
sort of the underlying serf mechanism
that underpins console you have knows
randomly probing each other at periodic
intervals to determine if the note is
still healthy and that feeds into the
catalog so if a node has you know if it
nodes not reachable at the surf layer
then it'll after a few confirmations
that know it'll be declared dead and
there will those services that were on
that node won't be given out as healthy
services to other nodes that's kind of
the basic bread and butter capability of
what the those those random probes are
for a neat sort of side effect of that
is that you're basically getting kind of
a randomized sample of the round-trip
time on your network between all your
nodes in a basically an automated
fashion all the time so in console 0 6
we implemented a network coordinate
subsystem which uses a set of techniques
around it's basically like set of
tomography techniques which is trying to
measure sort of the dimensions of
something by measurements from the ends
but what console does is it as it's
doing those probes it feeds those
round-trip time measurements into a
physics simulation which ends up
creating a set of coordinates for all
the nodes in your network and those
coordinates can be used to calculate the
round-trip time between any two nodes so
you get sort of an automatic model of
your network they'll let you make
interesting decisions about it so sort
of building on top of that one thing we
didn't talk a lot about is the console
let you also join different sets of
console servers together and what we
call the console LAN configuration so
you can have different you can have a
console in Europe and a console on the
east coast of the United States and then
a cluster in Asia and those server
clusters can know about each other and
you could discover services from one
data center in another one and what's
interesting is that that the network
tomography model can feed into that in a
very nautical a so we have
the sort of second feature I want to
talk about so they call prepared queries
so in console you can define you know
you can look up a service locally you
can also define something called the
prepared query which can have a policy
like if there are none locally give me
an instance try the next three closest
data centers by round-trip time and see
if you can find an instance in any of
those and that can all be done
automatically with network tomography so
you can by defining a very very simple
you know like a three line JSON thing
registering uh prepare query you can
basically enable something like geo
failover and if your clients are using
the DNS interface you won't even have to
change your clients so it's pretty
awesome like you can say you know here
if I can't find a read grep of it here
just try the next three data centers and
consoled by maintaining that tomography
information will be able to calculate
well you know if it's failing and you
know if it's in San Francisco I'm gonna
try the aja one but if it's on the East
Coast I'm gonna fail over to Europe and
it consul will manage that architecture
on its own and if I data center goes
offline you'll get the next closest one
after that all that could be managed and
expressed in a really really simple way
as a DNS query that your application
does which is pretty unique when all the
sort of pieces of console come together
like that that really kind of drives
home what you were talking about earlier
about other tools and having different
pieces of the puzzle and layers and
whatnot I can see you know we stack up
enough Turtles and we have a fairly
awesome kind of functionality there yeah
and my only other sort of thought was
it's definitely I would encourage people
to run the agent and experiment with it
you know the agent on its own can do
some basic health checking without you
really configuring anything and that's a
good way to get a little experience with
how it works before you've actually tied
it anything critical in your application
and things like the network tomography
can give you some neat information
basically without doing anything without
creating a bunch of network load or a
lot of risk and then you can sort of
build on other features over time but
it's pretty easy to get started okay so
how can people follow you console or the
other open source projects from Hoshi
core anything you give us we can put
to the shownotes oh if you don't need to
spell out URLs or anything but sure
I'm slack bad pretty much everywhere so
Twitter and github the Hoshi Corp
Twitter account at S corp is good for
getting our latest blog posts and
announcements things like that it's also
a she Corp on github all of our most of
our open-source projects are there some
still live under Mitchell Hashimoto we
have we're trying to get a pretty
regular cadence of webinars going so you
can definitely watch for those or
there's a lot of information on YouTube
from past webinars and you know
conference presentations things like
that we have two conferences as well we
have an upcoming Hoshi conf
EU in Amsterdam and how she come for us
in Napa California so there's some ways
to get kind of face time with the hutch
for engineers through those and we're
there's a ton of you know sort of open
presentations and things like that so
there's lots of ways to find out about
the company all right that's great
thanks for your time James I've really
enjoyed our discussion and I hope our
listeners have too
this is Charles an Anderson for software
engineering radio thanks thanks for
listening to SC radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website @ SC - radio
now to provide feedback you can write
comments on each episode on the website
or write a review on itunes mention a
message us on twitter at SC radio or
search for the software engineering
radio group on Lane
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]